Guide to the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850-2008 and undated, bulk 1898-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Photographic Materials Series, 1888-2008 and undated, (22 boxes)
  The thousands of photographs in this series document the history of North Carolina Mutual Insurance through images of its employees and their families, buildings and other places, and company events. The images range from formal portraits and group shots to snapshots taken at banquets, conventions, meetings, on trips, and around the office. There are many 19th century photographs of NCM leaders and their families, staff, including women workers, the earliest home office buildings, office interiors, and community events. Individuals depicted in later images include NCM officers, employees, their families, and prominent figures such as Robert F. Kennedy, Martin Luther King, Jr., Spiro Agnew, Jesse Jackson, ambassadors, and other politicians. Many significant original images were reproduced by NCM in various sizes and for various purposes; some of these reappear in the Exhibits Series material. The bulk of the 20th century images were produced by the Public Relations Department for The Whetstone and The Pilot and are therefore often marked for cropping and resizing. Although some images are captioned with names, years, and locations, many are unmarked and many dates have been estimated. Some related paper material, such as clippings, biographical sketches, speeches, copies of publications, and memos transmitting the images, can also be found with the prints.
  Materials are arranged into subseries by medium, but there are also slides, negatives, and negative reproductions found with corresponding photographs in the Prints Subseries. Comprising the bulk of the series, the Prints Subseries is arranged into Events, Historic Images, Other Public Relations, People, and Places Subseries. However, many of the images in these subseries overlap. Related items are also found in the Exhibit Material Series.
  Large-format photographs and albums are located in the Oversize Prints section listed at the end of this series. These items include historic images of the company's early offices, portraits of senior administrators, group shots at banquets and other events, and images of the NCM home office buildings. Sizes range from 11x14" to approx. 32x40", as well as a very large panoramic print of the early home office on Parrish Street, 27x75" (closed to use until conservation treatment is completed).
  - Negatives Subseries, 1900-2008 and undated
    Contains negatives and negative reproductions stored separately from prints. Items are arranged in loose chronological order and then into broad categories by content. Negatives directly associated with prints are located in the Prints Subseries.
    - People and places, 1900-1950, (21 negatives) (Box 113)
    - People, events, and places, 1940-1968, (11 negatives)
    - People, 1960-1980, (13 negatives)
    - Events, 1960-1980, (3 negatives)
    - People and office, 1980-1990, (2 folders; 25 negatives)
    - Events, 1980-1990, (6 folders; 57 negatives)
    - People and office, 1990-2000, (2 folders; 20 negatives) (Box 114)
    - Events, 1990-2000, (3 folders; 46 negatives)
    - People, 2000-2008, (3 folders; 9 negatives)
  - Photographic Prints Subseries, 1888-2008 and undated
    Mostly produced by the Public Relations department for publications such as The Whetstone and The Pilot, the prints are arranged into Events, Historic Images, Other Public Relations, People, and Places subseries, and within, chronologically. Negatives and slides directly associated with prints and related paper material are also located in this subseries. Many other large-format images are found in the Oversize Prints subseries listed at the end of the series.
    - Events, 1944-2008 and undated
      Arranged chronologically, these images depict banquets, conventions, trips, and meetings hosted or attended by NCM staff. Most but not all were labeled. Significant events include annual meetings of the National Insurance Association, a 1964 speech by Robert F. Kennedy, a 1964 trip to Mexico and Central America, and the celebration of NCM's 85th anniversary in 1983. Other events include awards ceremonies, retirement celebrations, the Annual Policy Holders' Meeting, Founders' Day, enrollment drives, and charitable events, such as an AIDS Walk and blood drives. Prominent event titles are included. Individuals depicted include NCM officers, employees, their families, politicians, and figures such as Robert F. Kennedy, Spiro Agnew, Jesse Jackson, and the Nigerian ambassador to the U.S. Some negatives and related paper documents are also included.
      - Conferences and meetings, 1944-1970, (2 folders; 114 prints) (Box 114)
      - Cloudburst, 1960-1985, (20 prints)
      - School in Agency Management, 1962, (1 print)
      - Various events, 1963 and undated, (6 prints)
      - Ambassador of Nigeria visit, 1964 Feb. 23, (18 prints)
      - Spaulding trip to Mexico and Central America, 1964, (76 prints)
      - Spaulding convention, 1967, (11 prints)
      - White House event, 1969 May 12, (2 prints)
      - NIA Convention in Richmond, 1970, (2 folders; 50 prints)
      - John Avery Boys' Club event, circa 1970s, (2 prints) (Box 115)
      - Events, 1970-1980, (4 prints)
      - NIA Convention in Houston, 1980, (2 folders; 68 prints)
      - Tailgate party, 1980 Sept., (20 prints)
      - Events, 1980-1990, (3 folders; 263 prints)
      - NIA Convention in Atlanta, 1981, (45 prints)
      - 85th Anniversary events, 1983, (8 of 18 folders; 175 prints)
      - 85th Anniversary events, 1983, (10 of 18 folders; 139 prints) (Box 116)
      - Various events, 1980s, (3 prints)
      - Dr. Cleland Tribute, 1985, (14 prints)
      - Russell Blunt Reception, 1986, (9 prints)
      - Annual Policy Holder's Meeting, 1968, (5 prints)
      - Blood drive, circa 1986, (13 prints)
      - Olympic Festival, 1987, (18 prints)
      - Sales Manager School, 1987, (43 prints)
      - Awards luncheon, 1989 May 19, (12 prints)
      - Convention and trip snapshots, 1989-1995, (2 folders; 166 prints)
      - Field Accounting System training, circa 1990, (48 prints)
      - Fellowship event, circa 1990, (37 prints)
      - 94th Founders Day, 1992, (60 prints)
      - Ron Brown Reception, 1992, (9 prints)
      - Annual Policyholders' Meeting, 1993, 1994, (2 folders)
      - Proactive Management Workshop, 1994, (1 print)
      - Events, 1990-2000, (1 of 18 folders; 52 prints)
      - Events, 1990-2000, (8 of 18 folders; 942 prints) (Box 117)
      - Events, 1990-2000, (9 of 18 folders; 748 prints) (Box 118)
      - Johnny Cochran reception, 1996, (7 prints)
      - Stagville event, 1997, (89 prints)
      - Events, 2003-2008, (10 of 11 folders; 919 prints) (Box 119)
      - Founders' Day album, 2003, (1 photo album) (Box 120)
      - Events, 2000-2008 (1 of 11 folders; 132 prints) (Box 121)
      - National Insurance Association (NIA) convention, 2003, (2 folders; 267 prints)
      - NCCU event, 2004, (205 prints)
    - Historic Images, 1888-1952 and undated
      Contains early black-and-white images of officers, employees, their family members, corporate meetings, the NCM office, and groups related to NCM, such as Thrift Clubs, musical groups, and sports teams. Other historic images can also be found in the People Subseries. Large-format historical images of the NCM offices and its officers and employees are also found in the Oversize Prints section at the end of this series; sizes range from 11x14" to approx. 32x40"; there is also an extremely large panoramic print 27x75" of the Parrish Street home office, closed to use until conservation treatment is completed. Arranged by content in loose chronological order.
      - John Merrick and family, circa 1885-1915, (3 folders; 12 prints) (Box 121)
      - Officers, circa 1890-1930s, (4 prints)
      - Home office clerks, 1909, (1 print)
      - Mrs. C.S. Moore; Booker and Charles Spaulding, Jr., circa 1910, (2 prints)
      - Merrick residence, circa 1910, (2 prints)
      - Booker T. Washington visit, 1910, (3 prints)
      - Office images, circa 1910-1940, (8 prints)
      - A.M. Moore, 1919-1923, (4 prints)
      - C.C. Spaulding, circa 1920-1952, (2 folders; 49 prints)
      - Meetings, circa 1920-1940, (7 prints) (Box 122)
      - People, circa 1920-1950, (37 prints)
      - Glee Club, Quintet, and sheet music for Dreams, circa 1929, (4 prints)
      - Merrick family, circa 1930-1960, (10 prints)
      - William Kennedy, Jr., circa 1930, (2 prints)
      - Thrift Clubs, circa 1933-1941, (19 prints)
      - Tennis championship, 1938 Sept. 3, (1 print)
      - Mrs. E.H. Berry and daughter, 1939-1944, (10 prints)
      - Model of office, circa 1930, (1 print)
      - Payment of first claim in Atlanta office, circa 1940, (1 print)
      - Master contract delivery, 1945 Mar., (1 print)
      - Basketball team, undated, (1 print)
      - Historic images photograph album assembled by NCM staff, 1920s-1960s (Box 122.1)
        Collection of 132 black-and-white photographs ranging in size from approx. 3x4" to 8x10", with three predominant types of images appearing in this order: the exterior of the home office on Parrish Street in Durham; interiors from the 1920s-1940s, including many early departments and their staff and equipment; and portraits of officers and other staff. Many of the subjects are identified on the back of the print. A series of commercially-made images of the medical and other departments in the 1940s are particularly of note. A few image slots are empty (#16, 134-137).
    - Other Public Relations Files, 1942-2008
      Arranged in loose chronological order, subseries contains intermixed images, almost all black-and-white, of events, people, and places, produced by the Public Relations Department for exhibits and publications such as The Whetstone and The Pilot. Some folders are related to specific issues of publications or composite pages while others are more intermixed. Many of the images in this subseries overlap with other subseries. Those depicted include NCM officers, employees, their families, policy holders, politicians, and prominent figures such as Robert F. Kennedy, Martin Luther King, Jr., and Jesse Jackson. Some negatives, reprints of older images, clippings, and related paper materials are also included. The bulk of the material dates from the 1960s.
      - PR, 1942-1987, (4 folders; 125 prints) (Box 122)
      - PR, 1950-1970, (4 of 5 folders; 165 prints)
      - PR, 1950-1970, (1 of 5 folders; 35 prints) (Box 123)
      - PR, 1950-1990, (2 folders; 31 prints)
      - PR, 1950-2000, (15 prints)
      - PR, 1960-1970, (14 of 25 folders; 362 prints)
      - PR, 1960-1970, (11 of 25 folders; 290 prints) (Box 124)
      - The Pilot materials, 1960-1980, (3 folders; 143 prints)
      - PR, 1960-1980, (6 folders; 111 prints)
      - PR, 1970-1980, (7 folders; 190 prints) (Box 125)
      - PR, 1970-1990, (4 folders; 81 prints)
      - PR, 1980-1990, (6 of 12 folders; 219 prints)
      - PR, 1980-1990, (6 of 12 folders; 123 prints) (Box 126)
      - PR, 1980-2000, (10 folders; 483 prints)
      - PR, 1980-2008, (25 prints)
      - PR, 1990-2000, (3 folders; 81 prints)
      - Collins scrapbook, 1992-1995, (21 prints) (Box 127)
      - Exhibit photographs, (6 folders; 183 prints)
        Contains reprints of photographs and drawings from different periods in NCM history, compiled for exhibits in the 1980-2000 period.
      - Exhibit photos from NIA Convention, 2003, (11 prints)
    - People, 1910-2008
      Arranged into employees, officers, and other people sub-groupings.
      - Employees, 1910-2008
        Contains portraits and group photographs of NCM employees from the home office and various district offices. In addition to headshots, employees are shown working and attending various events. Arranged by location, when possible.
        - Baltimore district, 1940-1962, (36 prints) (Box 127)
        - Birmingham district, 1940-1970, (51 prints)
        - Chicago district, 1950-1970, (19 prints) (Box 128)
        - Georgia district, circa 1910-1980, (3 folders; 115 prints)
        - Group shots of employees from various districts, 1961-1968 and undated, (8 prints)
        - Los Angeles district, circa 1960, (25 prints)
        - Newark district, 1950-1970, (63 prints)
        - Norfolk district, 1993, (1 print)
        - North Carolina district, circa 1930-2000, (5 folders; 246 prints)
        - Pennsylvania district, 1940-1980, (109 prints)
        - South Carolina district, circa 1920-1980, (90 prints)
        - Tennessee district, 1930-1980, (2 folders; 117 prints)
        - Washington DC district, 1930-1965, (54 prints) (Box 129)
        - Women, 1926-2008, (7 folders; 106 prints)
        - Other employees, 1940-2000, (8 folders; 422 prints)
        - Other employees, 1975-2008, (1 of 8 folders; 13 prints)
        - Other employees, 1975-2008, (7 of 8 folders; 300 prints) (Box 130)
      - Officers, 1910-2008
        Contains portraits and group photographs of NCM presidents, officers, Board of Directors, and Executive Committee. Images of officers' family members are also included. Contains formal portraits, group photographs, and snapshots taken at various events. Arranged in loose chronological order.
        - Merrick, Kennedy Jr., Kennedy III, and Sloan headshots, 1910-1990, (8 prints) (Box 130)
        - Board of Directors, 1929-1995, (4 folders; 69 prints)
        - C.C. Spaulding, circa 1940-1952, (14 prints)
        - C.C. Spaulding, Cox, and Merrick visit to Atlanta, 1934, (1 print)
        - J.L. Wheeler, 1943-1957, (9 prints)
        - W.A. Clement, 1950-1998, (2 folders; 79 prints)
        - Joseph W. Goodloe, 1952-1972, (2 folders; 75 prints)
        - Officers at various events, 1955-1978, (2 of 5 folders; 82 prints)
        - Unidentified male executive with glasses and Shriners' lapel pin, probably 1950s
        - W. A. Clement and Asa Spaulding, circa 1960, (3 photo albums) (Box 131)
        - Officers at various events, 1955-1978, (3 of 5 folders; 109 prints) (Box 132)
        - Asa T. Spaulding, 1956-1968, (2 folders; 68 prints)
        - William J. Kennedy, III, circa 1970s-1986, (2 folders; 14 prints)
        - Executive Committee, 1987-1988, (10 prints)
        - Bert Collins, 1987-1996, (2 folders; 30 prints)
        - William J. Kennedy, III and Bert Collins, circa 1990, (60 prints)
        - James Speed, 2004-2008, (27 prints)
      - Other People, 1930-2008
        Contains various portraits and group photographs of employees, family members, policy holders, executives from other insurance companies, scholarship recipients, and HBCU administrators. Many are currently unidentified. Arranged in loose chronological order.
        - Policy holders, 1930-1970, (141 prints) (Box 132)
        - University and high school students, 1935-1965, (76 prints)
        - Merrick and Moore Scholars, 1938-1970, (73 prints)
        - Group shots, 1940-1965, (24 prints)
        - Military service, circa 1945-1970, (10 prints) (Box 133)
        - Employees, policy holders, and other people, 1945-1990, (4 folders; 220 prints)
        - HBCU administrators, 1950-1970, (22 prints)
        - People, 1980-2008, (7 folders; 176 prints)
    - Places, 1905-2008
      Primarily contains images of the North Carolina Mutual physical plant, including different office buildings, men and women staff members on the job, workspaces, equipment, mainframes, decorations for specific events, and the construction of the 1965 home office. Includes photographic images of the original office buildings from circa 1900 to an architect's rendering of the new home office, circa 1963. Other images of the home offices can be found in oversize photo boxes and in the exhibits series. Of particular interest are a series of images of NCM employees' homes, which are labelled with the employee's name, rank, and city. Also included are scenes in Durham, N.C. and snapshots from business trips to Puerto Rico and Miami.
      - Employees' homes, 1930-1960, (52 prints) (Box 133)
      - NCM home office, front of frame building, circa 1900 (exhibit reproduction)
      - Physical plant and office scenes, and home office buildings, 1905-2008, (9 folders; 154 prints)
      - Hurricane Hugo damage, 1989, (16 prints) (Box 134)
      - Business trip snapshots, circa 1988-1995, (46 prints)
      - List of digital images of a variety of locations, 2007
    - Oversized Prints
      - Robert F. Kennedy at NIA convention album, 1962 (Box OV27)
      - Meeting album, 1985 (Box OV28)
      - Marketing Mid-Year Conference album, 1993
      - Event album, 1994 (Box OV29)
      - Annual Policyholders' Meeting, circa 2004
      - Historic Images, (4 folders) (Box OV30)
      - Historic Images, (5 folders) (Box OV31)
      - Events, People, Places, (7 folders) (Box OV32)
      - Historic Images, People, Places, (6 folders) (Box OV33)
      - Historic Images, Events, (8 folders) (Box OV34)
      - Historic Images, Events, (1 folder) (Box OV38)
      - NCM District Managers' meeting, circa 1940s; 60th anniversary banquet, 1958, (1 folder) (Box OV45)
      - Very large panoramic photograph mounted on board, 27x75" (Opaperfolder 6)
        [Not open to use due to fragile nature of item. Slated for conservation treatment.]
  - Slides Subseries, 1960-2005
    Contains slides stored separately from prints. Items are arranged in loose chronological order. Slides directly associated with prints are located in the Prints Subseries.
    - Asa Spaulding, circa 1960 (Box 134)
    - Events and people, 1989
    - People and office, 2000-2005
- Printed Materials Series, 1903-2008 and undated, bulk 1920s-1990s, (51 boxes)
  Arranged into the following subseries: NCM Publications, Non-NCM Publications, and Periodical Clippings. The first two subseries are further subdivided into two large format groupings: Pamphlets and Other Publications, and Serials. These files were assembled by NCM staff, and offer a rich array of material on African American history, culture, and businesses. Formats include essays, reports, pamphlets, brochures, fliers, newsletters, newspapers, journals, popular serials, internal publications, promotional literature, and obituaries. The substantial clippings file was assembled by the Public Relations Department, and is arranged topically; there are significant amounts of materials on the civil rights movement.
  There are also oversize sections at the end of each subseries, chiefly housing newspapers and other serials; early issues of Durham newspapers can be found here, as well as issues of mainstream magazines such as Ebony. The Non-NCM subseries in addition contains a large sub-grouping of print items related to Durham's historically black North Carolina Central University, including campus newspapers and events programs. Subseries and their contents are fully described below.
  - NCM Publications Subseries, 1903-2008 and undated
    - Pamphlets and Other Publications
      Various publications issued by North Carolina Mutual, including programs from memorial services; publications commemorating company anniversaries and the opening of new offices; The Mutual Album (a booklet containing photographs and biographies of NCM's founders and early employees); Education in our Democracy (a reprint of a speech that W.J. Kennedy, Jr. gave at Fort Valley State College); The Negro's Adventures in the Field of Life Insurance and Partners in Business (instructional tracts written by W.J. Kennedy, Jr. and Asa T. Spaulding, respectively); and various sales, promotional, and recruitment material, and training manuals. Arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
      - A Glossary of Insurance and Insurance-Related Terms, undated (Box 135)
      - Annual Report 1994, (3 folders)
      - Black Achievement, calendars, 1977-1979
      - Charters, bylaws, and resolutions, 1971-1984
      - Cloudburst All-Stars, 1985
      - Cruise West Indies and Caribbean, 1961 May
      - Dedication Festival for Mutual Plaza, Mar. 28-Apr. 2
      - Education in our Democracy, undated
      - Employee wellness program, 2002
      - Facts about African Americans pamphlets, undated
      - Founders' days/anniversaries, 1969-2008
      - Founders Memorial Services, pamphlet, 1983
      - Funerals and memorial services, 1944-2005, (2 folders)
      - Health bulletin, undated
      - Home office ground-breaking/dedication, 1963-1966
      - Internal promotional material, 1961-1985, (3 folders)
      - Internal promotional material, 1986-1987 and undated, (2 folders)
      - Living and Working Together the Mutual's Way, 1953
      - Memorial Service for Deborah Watts Hill, pamphlet, 1993
      - Music recital program, undated
      - The Negro's Adventures in the Field of Life Insurance, 1934-1937, (3 folders)
      - North Carolina Mutual: A Symbol, 1960-1964
      - Office openings, 1946-1950 (Box 136)
      - Office and officer images, undated
      - Partners in Business, 1940
      - Proceedings of the Annual Agents' Conference, 1920
      - Program honoring Asa Spaulding, 1959
      - Remington Rand Punched-Card Applications, undated
      - Retirees Anniversary Banquet, pamphlet, 2005
      - Sales and promotional material, undated, (10 folders)
      - Statistical Bulletin, 1923
      - Training manuals/guides, 1927-1988 and undated, (6 folders)
      - You and Your Company handbook, after 1965
      - Your Career recruitment pamphlet, undated
    - NCM Serials
      Serials printed by NCM for distribution to its employees. Consists primarily of The Review and The Whetstone, some groups of which were placed in binders. A binder with mixed contents contains various NCM publications, including an issue of The Whetstone (second quarter 1963); two issues of The Mutual; a pamphlet about the origins and history of the company (dated November 23, 1921); and the proceedings of the Annual Agents' Conference of 1920. Listing includes oversize material, found at end of grouping. Arranged alphabetically by title, then chronologically within.
      - The Hotline, 1988-1997 (Box 137)
      - The North Carolina Mutual cover, 1903 Sept., clippings 1906 Jan.
      - The Mutual, 1923 June, 1923 Nov., 1924 Apr., 1927 Apr., 1929
      - Newsorama, 1960-1961
      - The Review, 1933-1966 Sept., (11 folders)
      - The Review, 1966 Oct.-1985 Sept., (15 folders) (Box 138)
      - The Review, 1986-1998, (19 folders) (Box 139)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1956-1957 June, (3 binders) (Box 140)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1957 July-1959 June, (4 binders) (Box 141)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1960-1961, (4 binders) (Box 142)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1962-1963, (3 binders) (Box 143)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1963-1964 Dec., (4 binders) (Box 144)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1965, (3 binders) (Box 145)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1966, (2 binders) (Box 146)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1967, (2 binders) (Box 147)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1968, (2 binders) (Box 148)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1969-1970, (3 binders) (Box 149)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1971-1972, (3 binders) (Box 150)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1972-1974, (3 binders) (Box 151)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1976-1977, (3 binders) (Box 152)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1977-1978, (2 binders) (Box 153)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1979-1981, (2 binders) (Box 154)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1982-1985, (2 binders) (Box 155)
      - The Review (bound issues), 1989, (1 binder) (Box 156)
      - The Whetstone, 1924-1931, (9 folders)
      - The Whetstone, 1932-1939, (13 folders) (Box 157)
      - The Whetstone, 1940-1952, (14 folders) (Box 158)